How many fingers are in this picture?
321, okay
If you answered six fingers
Congratulations
surpasses all AI products worldwide
whether it's ChatGPT, DeepSeek, or Doubao
Almost all large AI models firmly answer that there are five fingers.
five fingers
Most of them even provided details
pretending to be answering very seriously
What's even more outrageous is
After discussing the issue of misidentifying six fingers with ChatGPT
then ask him again with a picture of a normal hand
Yet it actually responded with 'six fingers'
This might be related to its memory function.
It will reference historical responses as contextual information.
Then after I disabled the memory function
the response returns to normal when asked again
This shows that not only does the model itself struggle to count fingers correctly
Even a tiny bit of contextual interference can affect its judgment.
Not to mention, wasn't GTA recently released
Wasn't it recently published GTF uh
GPT-5
I switched to a different account to ask GPT-5, and it actually answered correctly.
It seems this GPT-5 has something impressive.
As expected of the most powerful model on Earth, but wait...
I sent another picture with 8 fingers
Then, I sent another normal picture with five fingers
could it be that the finger issue has been widely discussed recently
has entered the GPT-5 corpus and been over-trained
of course
This might just be the result of my random draw
but at least it shows that all AI models
including the strongest model on Earth
when it comes to counting fingers, a seemingly simple task for humans
can't get it right
it must be related to some underlying model mechanism
So today we're going to explore this issue
Without further ado, let's get straight to the issue
The model's input consists of an image and a piece of text
The model's output is also a piece of text, which is very simple.
However, the input includes both images and text
They are in different forms.
The difficulty lies right here
We call this type of model that contains different types of information
called multimodal
Let's simplify it first
remove the image
only text remains
then this process is simply an ordinary
a large language model implemented based on the Transformer architecture
first perform tokenization on this text
then convert each word into a vector and input it into the model
Finally, the model outputs the probability distribution of the vocabulary.
thereby obtaining the predicted next word
Add the next word back to the end of the original text
iteration
continuously generating new words
This forms a response
Friends who are not familiar with this process can take a look at this video
will guide you from scratch to gain a basic understanding of AI principles
If you don't have time
it's also fine
Just treat the model as a black box, or a function.
Okay, this modality is a text-based large language model
After continuous efforts in recent years
has already become very mature
Then we just need to integrate the image into this model, and that's it.
So how do we incorporate this image?
The simplest idea is to first convert the image into a text
Then just concatenate it with another piece of text, wouldn't that work?
but the step of converting the image into text
Isn't it still a multimodal task?
still need to figure out a solution
Let's take it a step further and convert the image into a set of vectors
the same as the text part
For the model
The information I receive is just a bunch of vectors
I don't care
I don't know or care what you've been transformed from either
Done! So how do you turn a picture into a set of vectors?
This is nothing unusual.
using traditional convolutional neural networks or
or the ViT that emerged after the rise of Transformer
can transform images into a set of vectors
we generally refer to it as an image encoder
There are also many methods for the text part
we collectively refer to them as text encoders
So can we just concatenate these two sets of vectors and feed them directly to the model?
It's common sense that it's not possible
In large language models
Word vectors are trained to have semantic relationships between them
Simply put,
The word vector for 'man' and the word vector for 'woman' look quite similar
expressed in mathematical terms
that is, the dot product or cosine similarity between the two vectors is relatively large
Then, in another model, the generated image vectors
in the vector space of language models
like a foreign language
incompatible
They just don't speak the same language.
For example, in the vector space of large language models
an image of a dog is converted into a set of vectors
might instead be very close to a completely unrelated dog vector
then the final answer would definitely be all messed up
So this crucial step
is to align images and text in the same vector space
the vector converted from the image of a dog
and the vector converted from the word 'dog' are similar
This is called modality alignment
That is, mapping the features of different modalities to the same semantic space
So how do we achieve modality alignment?
It's very simple. First, you go online and find 400 million pairs of images and text.
Each image corresponds to a piece of text description
Then, each image is processed by the aforementioned image encoder to generate vectors
Each piece of text is also converted into a vector through the aforementioned text encoder.
arrange them like this
Next, perform a dot product between each image vector and text vector pairwise.
that is, the similarity is calculated
Pay attention to the set of results on the diagonal
the dot product of the matched pair of post and image vectors
We call these samples positive sample pairs
and hope that their dot product is as large as possible
The text pairs that do not match in other positions are called negative sample pairs.
and hope their dot product is as small as possible
This approach of bringing positive sample pairs closer
The machine learning method of pushing negative sample pairs apart is called contrastive learning.
With this method
we can then define the loss function
Then train for 18 days on 592 V100 GPUs
the job is done
Isn't it simple?
This is OpenAI
the classic multimodal model CLIP does
It indeed collected 400 million high-quality pairs of posts.
and open-sourced the model weights after training
for downstream tasks
Does this image look familiar?
That's right, it's the result we just explored step by step in our video.
To make it feel familiar to you
I even adjusted the colors to be the same
How about giving us a Triple Combo for support?
At this point, we can answer the question raised at the beginning of the video
Why can't such an advanced AI still count fingers correctly?
Because the fundamental approach of this model
still converts the image into text first
or to be precise, alignment and adjustment are performed in the semantic space
After passing through the image encoder here
the image retains only semantically expressive information
In effect, it's equivalent to first converting the image into a textual description
You might think, isn't it easy to describe a picture?
Let's play a little game
Here is a very, very simple picture
Describe this picture in words
Any number of words will do
Then, I will ask you a question about this picture
See if based solely on your verbal description
without looking at the original image
Can you answer my question
Alright, my questions are these.
Take a look, which ones can be accurately answered based on your text description
questions that can be accurately answered
So the emergence of the problem of miscounting fingers
it's not that the large language model is unintelligent
nor is it due to insufficient modality alignment
but this approach itself is bound to lead to such problems
in the CLIP paper
The authors also pointed out the limitations in this aspect
even with training on such a large scale
but its accuracy on the MNIST dataset for handwritten digit recognition
not even comparable to the simplest logistic regression model
Of course, solving this specific issue is quite straightforward
for example, using a simple YOLO model
can accurately recognize fingers
and can even accurately mark the precise locations
but to train this capability into a general-purpose
generalizable multimodal model
it's not a matter of the same dimension
Uh, at the end of the video, let me introduce
This is a new large-scale series I've planned
video called AI's 100 Questions and Solutions
By answering 100 perplexing questions in the field of AI
To give everyone a profound understanding of the underlying principles of a particular technology
hope that after watching this series
everyone can maintain a balanced perspective on AI
nor overly disappointed
for example, seeing an AI's score surpass that of humans
think humanity is doomed
seeing the issue of AI miscounting fingers
think AI is all idiots
Based on today's video explanation
you should also be able to feel
Since large language models are trained on vast amounts of text
so it excels at summarizing and generalizing based on text
even in wordplay and reasoning
are far superior to humans
but precisely because the overall logic is based on text
The textual content itself is essentially a translation of human thought
the output after a layer of conversion
Now we still have to first convert the image into text
and then perform logical reasoning based on text to understand the image
Then this strategy will inevitably fail to address the problem of recognizing image details.
Let's brainstorm a bit here
If our large models were no longer trained based on text
but trained based on human thinking
Then perhaps the path to true multimodal integration can be truly opened up
But what exactly is human thought?
It seems we are simultaneously using text-based models
to try to understand people's thinking, uh
This series is suitable for everyone to watch
If you are a non-technical audience
hope this series can help you establish a technical perspective
perspective on issues
avoid being misled by many marketing accounts
And if you are a technical student
You can also refer to the points mentioned in this video
points not fully explored, delve deeper
In short, feel free to watch this series of videos